<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="eclipse">
  <title>Using m2eclipse</title>

  <section id="eclipse-sect-working-maven-projects">
    <title>Working with Maven Projects</title>

    <para>The m2eclipse plugin also provides a set of features for working
    with Maven projects once they are inside of Eclipse. There are many
    features that ease the ability to use Maven in Eclipse so let’s dive right
    into them. In the previous section, I materialized a Maven project and
    selected a subproject from the Apache Camel project named camel-core.
    We’ll use that project to demonstrate these features.</para>

    <para>By right-clicking on the camel-core project, and selecting the Maven
    menu item, you can see the available Maven features. <xref
    linkend="fig-eclipse-available-features" /> shows a screenshot of
    this:</para>

    <figure id="fig-eclipse-available-features">
      <title>Available Maven Features</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="figs/web/eclipse_available-features.png"
                     scalefit="1" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/eclipse_available-features.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Notice in <xref linkend="fig-eclipse-available-features" /> the
    available Maven features for the camel-core project,
    including:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Adding dependencies and plugins</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Updating dependencies, snapshots and source folders</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Creating a Maven module</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Downloading the source</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Opening Project URLs such as the Project Web Page, Issue
          Tracker, Source Control, and Continuous Integration tool.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Enabling/Disabling workspace resolution, nested Maven modules
          and dependency management</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>These features are also big time savers so let’s review them
    briefly.</para>


    <section id="eclipse-sect-downloading-source">
      <title>Downloading Source</title>

      <para>If the central Maven repository contains a source artifact for a
      particular project, you can download the source from the repository and
      expose it to the Eclipse environment. When you are trying to debug a
      complex issue in Eclipse, nothing can be easier than being able to right
      click on a third-party dependency and drill into the code in the Eclipse
      debugger. Select this option, and m2eclipse will attempt to download the
      source artifact from the Maven repository. If it is unable to retrieve
      this source artifact, you should ask the maintainers of the project in
      question to upload the appropriate Maven source bundle to the central
      Maven repository.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="eclipse-sect-opening-project-pages">
      <title>Opening Project Pages</title>

      <para>A Maven <acronym>POM</acronym> contains some valuable
      <acronym>URL</acronym>s which a developer may need to consult. These are
      the project's web page, the <acronym>URL</acronym> for the source code
      repository, a <acronym>URL</acronym> for a continuous integration system
      like Hudson, and a <acronym>URL</acronym> for an issue tracker. If these
      <acronym>URL</acronym>s are present in a project's
      <acronym>POM</acronym>, m2eclipse will open these project pages in a
      browser.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="eclipse-sect-resolving-dependencies">
      <title>Resolving Dependencies</title>

      <para>You can configure a project to resolve dependencies from a
      workspace. This has the effect of altering the way that Maven locates
      dependency artifacts. If a project is configured to resolve dependencies
      from the workspace, these artifacts do not need to be present in your
      local repository. Assume that project-a and project-b are both in the
      same Eclipse workspace, and that project-a depends on project-b. If
      workspace resolution is disabled, the m2eclipse Maven build for
      <varname>project-a</varname> will only succeed if
      <varname>project-b</varname>'s artifact is present in the local
      repository. If workspace resolution is enabled, m2eclipse will resolve
      the dependency via the Eclipse workspace. In other words, when workspace
      resolution is enabled, project's don't have to be installed in the local
      repository to relate to one another.</para>

      <para>You can also disable dependency management. This has the effect of
      telling m2eclipse to stop trying to manage your project's classpath, and
      it will remove the Maven Dependencies classpath container from your
      project. If you do this, you are essentially on your own when it comes
      to managing your project's classpath.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="eclipse-sect-pom-form">
    <title>Using the Form-based POM Editor</title>

    <para>The latest release of the m2eclipse plugin has a form-based
    <acronym>POM</acronym> editor which allows you to edit every part of a
    project's <filename>pom.xml</filename> with an easy-to-use
    <acronym>GUI</acronym> interface. To open the <acronym>POM</acronym>
    Editor, click on a project's <filename>pom.xml</filename> file. If you've
    customized the editors for a pom.xml file, and the POM Editor is not the
    default editor, you may need to right-click on the file and choose "Open
    With... / Maven POM Editor". The <acronym>POM</acronym> Editor will then
    display the Overview tab as shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-eclipse-pom-edit-overview" />.</para>

    <note>
      <para>The Form-based POM Editor is only available if you selected the
      POM Editor component when you installed the m2eclipse Eclipse plugin.
      For more information about installing the m2eclipse plugin, see <xref
      linkend="installing-sect-install-m2eclipse" />.</para>
    </note>

    <para>One common complaint about Maven is that it forces a developer to
    confront large and often overwhelming <acronym>XML</acronym> documents in
    a highly complex multi-module project build. While the authors of this
    book believe this is a small price to pay for the flexibility of a tool
    like Maven, the graphical <acronym>POM</acronym> editor is a tool that
    makes it possible for people to use Maven without ever having to know
    about the <acronym>XML</acronym> structure behind a Maven
    <acronym>POM</acronym>.</para>

    <figure id="fig-eclipse-pom-edit-overview">
      <title>Overview Tab of POM Editor for idiom-core</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="figs/web/eclipse_pom-editor.png" scalefit="1" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/eclipse_pom-editor.pdf" scalefit="0"
                     width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The project shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-eclipse-pom-edit-overview" /> is a project with an
    <varname>artifactId</varname> of of <varname>idiom-core</varname>. You'll
    notice that most of the fields in this <varname>idiom-core</varname>
    project are blank. There is no <varname>groupId</varname> or
    <varname>version</varname> and there is no <acronym>SCM</acronym>
    information supplied in the <acronym>POM</acronym> editor. This is due to
    the fact that <varname>idiom-core</varname> inherits most of this
    information from a parent project named <varname>idiom</varname>. If we
    open the <filename>pom.xml</filename> for the parent project in the
    <acronym>POM</acronym> Editor we would see the Overview tab shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-eclipse-pom-editor-overview-parent" />.</para>

    <para>That “open folder” icon on the various list entries throughout the
    <acronym>POM</acronym> editor indicate that the corresponding entry is
    present in the Eclipse workspace and “jar” icon indicates artifacts which
    are referenced from the Maven repository. You can double-click on those
    entries in order to open its POM in the POM editor. This works for
    modules, dependencies, plugins and other elements that have corresponding
    Maven artifacts. Underlined labels in several <acronym>POM</acronym>
    editor sections represent hyperlinks which can be used to open the
    <acronym>POM</acronym> editor for corresponding Maven artifact.</para>

    <figure id="fig-eclipse-pom-editor-overview-parent">
      <title>Overview Tab of POM Editor for idiom Parent Project</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="figs/web/eclipse_pom-editor-parent.png"
                     scalefit="1" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/eclipse_pom-editor-parent.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>In this parent <acronym>POM</acronym>, we see that the
    <varname>groupId</varname> and <varname>version</varname> are defined and
    that the parent <acronym>POM</acronym> supplies much of the information
    which was missing in the <varname>idiom-core</varname> project. The
    <acronym>POM</acronym> editor is going to show you the contents of the
    <acronym>POM</acronym> that you are editing, and it will not show you any
    of the inherited values. If you wanted to look at the
    <varname>idiom-core</varname> project's effective <acronym>POM</acronym>
    in the <acronym>POM</acronym> editor, you can use “Show Effective POM”
    action from the tool-bar in the upper right-hand corner of the
    <acronym>POM</acronym> editor, which shows a left bracket and an equals
    sign on a page with a blue M. It will load the effective
    <acronym>POM</acronym> for <varname>idiom-code</varname> in the
    <acronym>POM</acronym> Editor as shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-eclipse-pom-editor-effective" />.</para>

    <figure id="fig-eclipse-pom-editor-effective">
      <title>Effective POM for idiom-core</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/eclipse_pom-editor-effective.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/eclipse_pom-editor-effective.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>This effective view of the <acronym>POM</acronym> merges the
    <varname>idiom-core</varname> <acronym>POM</acronym> with the ancestor
    <acronym>POM</acronym>s (the parent, the grandparent, etc.), similarly to
    “mvn help:effective-pom” command and displays the <acronym>POM</acronym>
    editor with the effective values. Because the <acronym>POM</acronym>
    editor is display a composite view of many different merged
    <acronym>POM</acronym>s, this effective <acronym>POM</acronym> Editor is
    read-only, and you will not be able to update any of the fields in this
    effective <acronym>POM</acronym> view.</para>

    <para>If you were looking at the <acronym>POM</acronym> editor for the
    idiom-core project as shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-eclipse-pom-edit-overview" />, you can also navigate to the
    parent <acronym>POM</acronym> using, ”Open Parent POM” action from the POM
    editor tool-bar in the upper right-hand of the <acronym>POM</acronym>
    editor.</para>

    <para>The <acronym>POM</acronym> editor shows a number of showing various
    information from the <acronym>POM</acronym>. The final tab exposes the
    <filename>pom.xml</filename> as an <acronym>XML</acronym> document. There
    is a dependencies tab shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-eclipse-pom-editor-dependencies" /> which exposes an
    easy-to-use interface for adding and editing dependencies to your project,
    as well as editing the <sgmltag>dependencyManagement</sgmltag> section of
    the <acronym>POM</acronym>. This dependency management screen is also
    integrated with the artifact searching facilities in the m2eclipse plugin.
    You can use actions from the editor sections, as well as Ctrl-Space typing
    assistance for the fields in “Dependency Details” section.</para>

    <para>If you need to know more about one of the artifacts, you can use
    “Open Web Page” action from “Dependency Details” section tool-bar to check
    the project web page.</para>

    <figure id="fig-eclipse-pom-editor-dependencies">
      <title>Dependencies Tab of the POM Editor</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="figs/web/eclipse_pom-editor-dependencies.png"
                     scalefit="1" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/eclipse_pom-editor-dependencies.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The build tab shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-eclipse-pom-editor-build" /> provides access to the contents
    of the build element. From this tab you can customize source directories,
    add extensions, change the default goal name, and add resources
    directories.</para>

    <figure id="fig-eclipse-pom-editor-build">
      <title>Build Tab of the POM Editor</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="figs/web/eclipse_pom-editor-build.png"
                     scalefit="1" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/eclipse_pom-editor-build.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>We only showed a small subset of the <acronym>POM</acronym> editor.
    If you are interested in seeing the rest of the tabs, please download and
    install the m2eclipse plugin.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="eclipse-sect-summary">
    <title>Summary</title>

    <para>m2eclipse is more than just a simple plugin which adds Maven support
    to Eclipse, it is a comprehensive integration that will make everything
    from creating new projects to locating third-party dependencies orders of
    magnitude easier. m2eclipse is the first step toward an
    <acronym>IDE</acronym> that is aware of the rich semantic treasure that is
    the central Maven repository. As more people come to use m2eclipse, more
    projects are going to be releasing Maven Archetypes, and more projects are
    going to see value in publishing source artifacts to the Maven repository.
    If you've tried to use Eclipse and Maven together without a tool that can
    comprehend the hierarchical project relationships that are central to any
    multi-module Maven project, you will know that the ability to work with
    nested projects is essential to smooth integration between the Eclipse
    <acronym>IDE</acronym> and Maven.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
