<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="installing">
  <title>Installing m2eclipse</title>

  <section id="installing-sect-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>To install the m2Eclipse plugin, you will need to install some
    prerequisites. You will need to be running Eclipse 3.2 or higher,
    <acronym>JDK</acronym> 1.4 or higher, and you will also need to make sure
    that Eclipse is running on a <acronym>JDK</acronym> and not a
    <acronym>JRE</acronym>. Once you have Eclipse and a compatible
    <acronym>JDK</acronym>, you will need to install two Eclipse plugins:
    Subclipse and Mylyn.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="installing-sect-prereq">
    <title>Installing Prerequisites</title>

    <para>You can install these prerequisites when you install m2eclipse, just
    add a new remote update site to Eclipse for each of the prerequisite
    components. To install these prerequisites, go to <guiicon>Help</guiicon>,
    <guisubmenu>Software Updates</guisubmenu>, <guimenuitem>Find and
    Install...</guimenuitem>. Selecting this menu item will load the
    Install/Update dialog box. Choose the "Search for new features to install"
    option and click <guibutton>Next</guibutton>. You will then be presented
    with a list of "Update sites to visit". Click <guibutton>New Remote
    Site...</guibutton>, and add a new update site for each new prerequisite.
    Add a new remote site for each plugin and then make sure that the remote
    site is selected. After you click <guibutton>Finish</guibutton>, Eclipse
    will then ask you to select plugins components to install. Select the
    components you want to install and Eclipse will download, install, and
    configure your plugins.</para>

    <para>Note that if you are using a recent build of Eclipse 3.4 (Ganymede)
    your plugin installation experience may be slightly different. In
    Ganymede, you will select <guimenu>Help</guimenu>, <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
    which will load the "Software Updates and Add-ons" dialog. In this dialog,
    choose the Available Software panel and click on <guibutton>Add
    Site...</guibutton> which will load the simple "Add Site" dialog. Enter
    the <acronym>URL</acronym> of the update site you wish to add and click
    <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. In the "Software Updates and Add-ons" dialog,
    the available plugins from an update site will appear as soon as the site
    is added. You can then select the modules you want to install and click
    the <guibutton>Install... </guibutton>button. Eclipse will then resolve
    all the dependencies for the selected plugins, and ask you to agree to the
    plugin license. After Eclipse installs new plugins, it will likely ask you
    for permission to restart.</para>

    <section id="installing-sect-install-subclipse">
      <title>Installing Subclipse</title>

      <para>To install Subclipse, use the Eclipse plugin update site listed
      below.<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Subclipse 1.2: <ulink
            url="http://subclipse.tigris.org/update_1.2.x">http://subclipse.tigris.org/update_1.2.x</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>For other versions of Subclipse, and for more information about
      the Subclipse plugin, please see the Subclipse project's web site at
      <ulink
      url="http://subclipse.tigris.org/">http://subclipse.tigris.org/</ulink>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="installing-sect-install-mylyn">
      <title>Installing Mylyn</title>

      <para>To install JIRA integration with Mylyn, add the Mylyn extras
      Eclipse update URL, you'll want to do this if your organization uses
      <ulink url="http://www.atlassian.com/software/jira/">Atlassian's
      JIRA</ulink> for issue tracking. To install Mylyn use the following
      update sites:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Mylyn (Eclipse 3.3): <ulink
            url="http://download.eclipse.org/tools/mylyn/update/e3.3">http://download.eclipse.org/tools/mylyn/update/e3.3
            </ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Mylyn (Eclipse 3.4): <ulink
            url="http://download.eclipse.org/tools/mylyn/update/e3.4">http://download.eclipse.org/tools/mylyn/update/e3.4</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Mylyn Extras (JIRA Support): <ulink
            url="http://download.eclipse.org/tools/mylyn/update/extras">http://download.eclipse.org/tools/mylyn/update/extras</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>For more information about the Mylyn project, see the Mylyn
      project's web site at <ulink
      url="http://www.eclipse.org/mylyn/">http://www.eclipse.org/mylyn/</ulink>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="installing-sect-install-aspectj">
      <title>Installing AspectJ Development Tools (AJDT)</title>

      <para>If you are installing the 0.9.4 release of m2eclipse, you may also
      want to install both the Web Tools Platform (<acronym>WTP</acronym>) and
      the AspectJ Development Tools (<acronym>AJDT</acronym>). To install the
      <acronym>AJDT</acronym> use one of the following update URLs in
      Eclipse:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>AJDT (Eclipse 3.3): <ulink
            url="http://download.eclipse.org/tools/ajdt/33/update">http://download.eclipse.org/tools/ajdt/33/update</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>AJDT (Eclipse 3.4): <ulink
            url="http://download.eclipse.org/tools/ajdt/34/dev/update">http://download.eclipse.org/tools/ajdt/34/dev/update</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>For more information about the AJDT project, see the AJDT
      project's web site at <ulink
      url="http://www.eclipse.org/ajdt/">http://www.eclipse.org/ajdt/</ulink>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="installing-sect-install-wtp">
      <title>Installing the Web Tools Platform (WTP)</title>

      <para>To install the Web Tools Platform (<acronym>WTP</acronym>). Use
      one of the following update URLs in Eclipse, or just look for the Web
      Tools Project in the Discovery Site which should already be in your
      Eclipse remote update sites list.<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>WTP: <ulink
            url="http://download.eclipse.org/webtools/updates/">http://download.eclipse.org/webtools/updates/</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>For more information about the Web Tools Platform, see the Web
      Tools Platform project's web site at <ulink
      url="http://www.eclipse.org/webtools/">http://www.eclipse.org/webtools/</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="installing-sect-install-m2eclipse">
    <title>Installing m2eclipse</title>

    <para>Once you've installed the prerequisites, you can install the
    m2eclipse plugin from the following Eclipse update URL:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>m2eclipse Plugin: <ulink
          url="http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/update/">http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/update/</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>If you would like to install the latest snapshot development version
    of the plugin, you should use the update-dev <acronym>URL</acronym>
    instead of the previous <acronym>URL</acronym>:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>m2eclipse Plugin (Development Snapshot): <ulink
          url="http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/update-dev/">http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/update-dev/</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>To install m2eclipse, just add a the appropriate update site for
    m2eclipse. Go to <guiicon>Help</guiicon>, <guisubmenu>Software
    Updates</guisubmenu>, <guimenuitem>Find and Install...</guimenuitem>.
    Selecting this menu item will load the Install/Update dialog box. Choose
    the "Search for new features to install" option and click
    <guibutton>Next</guibutton>. You will then be presented with a list of
    "Update sites to visit". Click <guibutton>New Remote Site...</guibutton>,
    and add a new update site for m2eclipse. Add a new remote site for
    m2eclipse and then make sure that the remote site is selected. After you
    click <guibutton>Finish</guibutton>, Eclipse will then ask you to select
    plugins components to install. Select the components you want to install
    and Eclipse will download, install, and configure m2eclipse.</para>

    <para>If you've installed the plugin successfully, you should see a Maven
    option in the list of preferences options when you go to
    <guiicon>Window</guiicon>,
    <guimenuitem>Preferences...</guimenuitem>.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>