<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.sonatype.com/tmp/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="dependencies">
  <title>Using m2eclipse</title>

  <section id="whatever">
    <section id="dependencies-sect-adding-updating">
      <title>Adding and Updating Dependencies and Plugins</title>

      <para>Let’s say we’d like to add a dependency or a plugin to the
      <varname>camel-core</varname> <acronym>POM</acronym>. For the sake of
      demonstration, we're going to add <varname>commons-lang</varname> as a
      dependency. (Please note that the functionality for adding a dependency
      or a plugin is exactly the same so we’ll demonstrate it by adding a
      dependency.)</para>

      <para>m2eclipse offers two options for adding dependencies to a project.
      The first option is by manually editing the <acronym>POM</acronym> file
      to type in the <acronym>XML</acronym> to add the dependency. The
      downside to manually editing the <acronym>POM</acronym> file to add a
      dependency is that you must already know the information about the
      artifact, or use the features discussed in the next section to manually
      locate the artifact information in the repository indexes. The upside is
      that after manually adding the dependency and saving the
      <acronym>POM</acronym>, the project’s Maven Dependencies container will
      be automatically updated to include the new dependency. <xref
      linkend="fig-dependencies-manual-add" /> shows how I added a dependency
      for <varname>commons-lang</varname> to the
      <varname>camel-console</varname> <acronym>POM</acronym> and the Maven
      Dependencies container was automatically updated to included it:</para>

      <figure id="fig-dependencies-manual-add">
        <title>Manually Adding a Dependency to the Project's POM</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                       fileref="figs/web/eclipse_add-manual-depend.png"
                       scalefit="1" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/eclipse_add-manual-depend.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Manually adding a dependency works well but requires more work
      than the second approach. Upon manually adding the dependency element to
      the <acronym>POM</acronym>, the Eclipse progress in the lower right-hand
      corner of the Eclipse workbench reflects the action as shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-dependencies-update-depends" />:</para>

      <figure id="fig-dependencies-update-depends">
        <title>Updating Maven Dependencies</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                       fileref="figs/web/eclipse_updating-depends.png"
                       scalefit="1" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/eclipse_updating-depends.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The second option for adding a dependency is much easier because
      you don’t have to know any information about the artifact other than its
      <varname>groupId</varname>. <xref
      linkend="fig-dependencies-search-depend" /> shows this
      functionality:</para>

      <figure id="fig-dependencies-search-depend">
        <title>Searching for a Dependency</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                       fileref="figs/web/eclipse_add-depend3.png" scalefit="1"
                       width="100%" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/eclipse_add-depend3.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>By simply entering a <varname>groupId</varname> into the query
      field, m2eclipse queries the repository indexes and even shows a version
      of the artifact that is currently in my local Maven repository. This
      option is preferred because it is such a tremendous time saver. With
      m2eclipse, you no longer need to hunt through the central Maven
      repository for an artifact version.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dependencies-sect-downloading-source">
      <title>Downloading Source</title>

      <para>If the central Maven repository contains a source artifact for a
      particular project, you can download the source from the repository and
      expose it to the Eclipse environment. When you are trying to debug a
      complex issue in Eclipse, nothing can be easier than being able to right
      click on a third-party dependency and drill into the code in the Eclipse
      debugger. Select this option, and m2eclipse will attempt to download the
      source artifact from the Maven repository. If it is unable to retrieve
      this source artifact, you should ask the maintainers of the project in
      question to upload the appropriate Maven source bundle to the central
      Maven repository.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dependencies-sect-opening-project-pages">
      <title>Opening Project Pages</title>

      <para>A Maven <acronym>POM</acronym> contains some valuable
      <acronym>URL</acronym>s which a developer may need to consult. These are
      the project's web page, the <acronym>URL</acronym> for the source code
      repository, a <acronym>URL</acronym> for a continuous integration system
      like Hudson, and a <acronym>URL</acronym> for an issue tracker. If these
      <acronym>URL</acronym>s are present in a project's
      <acronym>POM</acronym>, m2eclipse will open these project pages in a
      browser.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dependencies-sect-resolving-dependencies">
      <title>Resolving Dependencies</title>

      <para>You can configure a project to resolve dependencies from a
      workspace. This has the effect of altering the way that Maven locates
      dependency artifacts. If a project is configured to resolve dependencies
      from the workspace, these artifacts do not need to be present in your
      local repository. Assume that project-a and project-b are both in the
      same Eclipse workspace, and that project-a depends on project-b. If
      workspace resolution is disabled, the m2eclipse Maven build for
      <varname>project-a</varname> will only succeed if
      <varname>project-b</varname>'s artifact is present in the local
      repository. If workspace resolution is enabled, m2eclipse will resolve
      the dependency via the Eclipse workspace. In other words, when workspace
      resolution is enabled, project's don't have to be installed in the local
      repository to relate to one another.</para>

      <para>You can also disable dependency management. This has the effect of
      telling m2eclipse to stop trying to manage your project's classpath, and
      it will remove the Maven Dependencies classpath container from your
      project. If you do this, you are essentially on your own when it comes
      to managing your project's classpath.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="dependencies-sect-analyze-depend">
    <title>Analyzing Project Dependencies in m2eclipse</title>

    <para>The latest release of m2eclipse contains a <acronym>POM</acronym>
    editor which provides some dependency analysis tools. These tools promise
    to change the way people maintain and monitor a project's transitive
    dependencies. One of the main attractions to Maven is the fact that it
    manages a project's dependencies. If you are writing an application which
    depends on the Spring Framework's Hibernate3 integration, all you need to
    do is depend on the <varname>spring-hibernate3</varname> artifact from the
    Central Maven Repository. Maven then reads this artifact's
    <acronym>POM</acronym> and adds all of the necessary transitive
    dependencies. While this is a great feature that attracts people to using
    Maven in the first place, it can often become confusing with a project
    starts to depend on tens of dependencies, each with tens of transitive
    dependencies.</para>

    <para>Problems start to happen when you depend on a project with a poorly
    crafted <acronym>POM</acronym> which fails to flag dependencies as
    optional, or when you start encountering conflicts between transitive
    dependencies. If one of your requirements is to exclude a dependency like
    <varname>commons-logging</varname> or the <varname>servlet-api</varname>,
    or if you need to find out why a certain dependency is showing up under a
    specific scope you will frequently need to invoke the
    <varname>dependency:tree</varname> and
    <varname>dependency:resolve</varname> goals from the command-line to track
    down the offending transitive dependencies.</para>

    <para>This is where the <acronym>POM</acronym> editor in m2eclipse comes
    in handy. If you open a project with many dependencies, you can open the
    Dependency Tree tab and see a two-column display of dependencies as shown
    in <xref linkend="fig-dependencies-pom-editor-dependency-tree" />. The
    left-side of the panel displays a tree of dependencies. The first level of
    the tree consists of direct dependencies from your project, and each
    subsequent level lists the dependencies of each dependency. The left-hand
    side is a great way to figure out how a specific dependency made its way
    into your project's resolved dependencies. The right-hand side of this
    panel displays the resolved dependencies. This is the list of effective
    dependencies after all conflicts and scopes have been applied, and it is
    the effective list of dependencies that your project will use for
    compilation, testing, and packaging.</para>

    <figure id="fig-dependencies-pom-editor-dependency-tree">
      <title>Dependency Tree Tab of the POM Editor</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                     fileref="figs/web/eclipse_pom-editor-depend-tree.png"
                     scalefit="1" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/eclipse_pom-editor-depend-tree.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The feature which makes the Dependency Tree tab so valuable is that
    it can be used as an investigative tool to figure out how a specific
    dependency made it into the list of resolved dependencies. Searching and
    filtering functionality available in the editor makes it really easy to
    search and browse trough the project dependencies. You can use “Search”
    entry field from the editor tool-bar and “Sort” and “Filter” actions from
    “Dependency Hierarchy” and “Resolved Dependencies” sections to navigate
    trough dependencies. <xref
    linkend="fig-dependencies-pom-editor-locate-depend" /> shows what happens
    when you click on commons-logging in the "Resolved Dependencies" list.
    When filtering is enabled in “Dependencies Hierarchy” section, clicking on
    a resolved dependency filters the hierarchy on the left-hand side of the
    panel to show all of the node which contributed to the resolved
    dependency. If you are trying to get rid of a resolved dependency, you can
    use this tool to find out what dependencies (and what transitive
    dependencies) are contributing the artifact to your resolved dependencies.
    In other words, if you are trying to get rid of something like
    <varname>commons-logging</varname> from your dependency set, the
    Dependency Tree tab is the tool you will likely want to use.</para>

    <figure id="fig-dependencies-pom-editor-locate-depend">
      <title>Locating Dependencies in the Dependency Tree</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/eclipse_pom-editor-depend-tree-locate.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/eclipse_pom-editor-depend-tree-locate.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>m2eclipse also provides you with the ability to view your project's
    dependencies as a graph. <xref
    linkend="fig-dependencies-pom-editor-graph" /> shows the dependencies of
    <varname>idiom-core</varname>. The top-most box is the
    <varname>idiom-core</varname> project and the other dependencies are shown
    below it. Direct dependencies are linked from the top box and the
    transitive dependencies are linked from those. You can select a specific
    node in the graph to highlight the linked dependencies, or you can use the
    Search field at the top of the page to find matching nodes.</para>

    <para>Note that “open folder” icon on each graph node indicates that the
    corresponding artifact is present in the Eclipse workspace and “jar” icon
    indicates that the node's artifact is referenced from the Maven
    repository.</para>

    <figure id="fig-dependencies-pom-editor-graph">
      <title>Viewing the Dependencies of a Project as a Graph</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/eclipse_pom-editor-graph.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/eclipse_pom-editor-graph.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The graph presentation can be changed by right clicking in the
    editor. You can choose to show artifact ids, group ids, versions, scopes,
    or if you want to wrap node text or show icons. <xref
    linkend="fig-dependencies-pom-editor-graph-radial" /> shows the same graph
    from <xref linkend="fig-dependencies-pom-editor-graph" /> with a radial
    layout.</para>

    <figure id="fig-dependencies-pom-editor-graph-radial">
      <title>Radial Layout of Dependency Graph</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/eclipse_pom-editor-graph-radial.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/eclipse_pom-editor-graph-radial.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
</chapter>
