<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="installation">
  <title>Installing Maven</title>

  <para><indexterm>
      <primary>Apache Maven</primary>

      <secondary>installation of</secondary>
    </indexterm><indexterm>
      <primary>installing Maven</primary>
    </indexterm>This chapter contains very detailed instructions for
  installing Maven on a number of different platforms. Instead of assuming a
  level of familiarity with installing software and setting environment
  variables, we've opted to be as thorough as possible to minimize any
  problems that might arise do to a partial installation. The only thing this
  chapter assumes is that you've already installed a suitable <indexterm>
      <primary>Java Development Kit (JDK)</primary>
    </indexterm>Java Development Kit (<acronym>JDK</acronym>). If you are just
  interested in installation, you can move on to the rest of the book after
  reading through <xref linkend="installation-sect-maven-download"
  xrefstyle="select: title" /> and <xref
  linkend="installation-sect-maven-install" xrefstyle="select: title" />. If
  you are interested in the details of your Maven installation, this entire
  chapter will give you an overview of what you've installed and the meaning
  of the Apache Software License, Version 2.0.</para>

  <section id="installation-sect-java">
    <title>Verify your Java Installation</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Java Development Kit (JDK)</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Maven prerequisites</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Apache Maven</primary>

        <secondary>prerequisites</secondary>
      </indexterm>While Maven can run on Java 1.4, this book assumes that you
    are running at least Java 5. Go with the most recent stable Java
    Development Kit (<acronym>JDK</acronym>) available for your operating
    system. Either Java 5 or Java 6 will work with all of the examples in this
    book.</para>

    <para><screen><prompt moreinfo="none">% </prompt><command moreinfo="none">java -version</command>
java version "1.5.0_16"
Java(TM) 2 Runtime Environment, Standard Edition (build 1.5.0_16-b06-284)
Java HotSpot(TM) Client VM (build 1.5.0_16-133, mixed mode, sharing)
</screen></para>

    <para>Maven works with all certified Java<superscript>TM</superscript>
    compatible development kits, and a few non-certified implementations of
    Java. The examples in this book were written and tested against the
    official Java Development Kit releases downloaded from the Sun
    Microsystems web site. If you’re working with a Linux distribution, you
    may need to download Sun’s <acronym>JDK</acronym> yourself and make sure
    it’s the version you’re invoking (by running <command>java
    -version</command>). Now that Sun has open-sourced Java, this will
    hopefully improve in the future, and we’ll get the Sun
    <acronym>JRE</acronym> and <acronym>JDK</acronym> by default even in
    purist Linux distributions. Until that day, you may need to do some of
    your own downloading.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="installation-sect-maven-download">
    <title>Downloading Maven</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>downloading Maven</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Apache Maven</primary>

        <secondary>downloading</secondary>
      </indexterm>You can download Maven from the Apache Maven project website
    at <ulink
    url="http://maven.apache.org/download.html">http://maven.apache.org/download.html</ulink>.</para>

    <para>When downloading Maven, make sure you choose the latest version of
    Apache Maven from the Maven website. The latest version of Maven when this
    book was written was Maven ${maven.version}. If you are not familiar with
    the Apache Software License, you should familiarize yourself with the
    terms of the license before you start using the product.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="installation-sect-maven-install">
    <title>Installing Maven</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Apache Maven</primary>

        <secondary>installation of</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>installing Maven</primary>
      </indexterm>There are wide differences between operating systems such as
    Mac <acronym>OS X</acronym> and Microsoft Windows, and there are subtle
    differences between different versions of Windows. Luckily, the process of
    installing Maven on all of these operating systems is relatively painless
    and straightforward. The following sections outline the recommended
    best-practice for installing Maven on a variety of operating
    systems.</para>

    <section id="installation-sect-maven-osx">
      <title>Installing Maven on Mac OSX</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>installing Maven</primary>

          <secondary>on Mac OSX</secondary>
        </indexterm>You can download a binary release of Maven<indexterm>
          <primary>installing Maven</primary>

          <secondary sortas="Mac OS X">on Mac OS X</secondary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary sortas="maven @installing">Maven, installing</primary>

          <secondary sortas="Mac OS X">on Mac OS X</secondary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>Mac OS X, installing Maven on</primary>
        </indexterm> from <ulink
      url="http://maven.apache.org/download.html"></ulink>. Download the
      current release of Maven in a format that is convenient for you to work
      with. Pick an appropriate place for it to live, and expand the archive
      there. If you expanded the archive into the directory
      <filename>/usr/local/apache-maven-${maven.version}</filename>, you may
      want to create a symbolic link to make it easier to work with and to
      avoid the need to change any environment configuration when you upgrade
      to a newer version:</para>

      <screen>/usr/local % <command moreinfo="none">cd /usr/local
</command>/usr/local % <command moreinfo="none">ln -s apache-maven-${maven.version} maven
</command>/usr/local % <command>export M2_HOME=/usr/local/maven</command>
/usr/local % <command>export PATH=\${M2_HOME}/bin:\${PATH}</command></screen>

      <para>Once Maven is installed, you need to do a couple of things to make
      it work correctly. You need to add its <filename
      moreinfo="none">bin</filename> directory in the distribution (in this
      example, <filename moreinfo="none">/usr/local/maven/bin</filename>) to
      your command path. You also need to set the environment variable
      <varname>M2_HOME<indexterm>
          <primary>M2_HOME environment variable</primary>

          <secondary>Maven installation and</secondary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>PATH variable, Maven installation and</primary>
        </indexterm></varname> to the top-level directory you installed (in
      this example, <filename
      moreinfo="none">/usr/local/maven</filename>).</para>

      <note>
        <para>Installation instructions are the same for both
        <acronym>OSX</acronym> Tiger and <acronym>OSX</acronym> Leopard. It
        has been reported that Maven 2.0.6 is shipping with a preview release
        of XCode. If you have installed XCode, run <command>mvn</command> from
        the command-line to check availability. XCode installs Maven in
        <filename>/usr/share/maven</filename>. We recommend installing the
        most recent version of Maven ${maven.version} as there have been a
        number of critical bug fixes and improvements since Maven 2.0.6 was
        released.</para>
      </note>

      <para>You'll need to add both <envar>M2_HOME</envar> and
      <envar>PATH</envar> to a script that will run every time you login. To
      do this, add the following lines to
      <filename>.bash_login</filename>.</para>

      <programlisting>export M2_HOME=/usr/local/maven
export PATH=\${M2_HOME}/bin:\${PATH}</programlisting>

      <para>Once you've added these lines to your own environment, you will be
      able to run Maven from the command line.</para>

      <note>
        <para>These installation instructions assume that you are running
        bash.</para>
      </note>

      <section id="installation-sect-macports">
        <title>Installing Maven on OSX using MacPorts</title>

        <para><indexterm>
            <primary>installing Maven</primary>

            <secondary>on Mac OSX with MacPorts</secondary>
          </indexterm>If you are using MacPorts, you can install the maven2
        port by executing the following command-line:</para>

        <screen>$ <command>sudo port install maven2</command>
Password: ******
---&gt;  Fetching maven2
---&gt;  Attempting to fetch apache-maven-${maven.version}-bin.tar.bz2 
      from http://www.apache.org/dist/maven/binaries
---&gt;  Verifying checksum(s) for maven2
---&gt;  Extracting maven2
---&gt;  Configuring maven2
---&gt;  Building maven2 with target all
---&gt;  Staging maven2 into destroot
---&gt;  Installing maven2 ${maven.version}_0
---&gt;  Activating maven2 ${maven.version}_0
---&gt;  Cleaning maven2
</screen>

        <para>For more information about the maven2 port, see the maven2
        <filename><ulink
        url="http://trac.macports.org/browser/trunk/dports/java/maven2/Portfile">Portfile</ulink></filename>.
        For more information about MacPorts and how to install it, see the
        <ulink url="http://www.macports.org/index.php">MacPorts project
        page</ulink>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="installation-sect-windows">
      <title>Installing Maven on Microsoft Windows</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>installing Maven</primary>

          <secondary>on Windows</secondary>
        </indexterm>Installing Maven on Windows is very similar to installing
      Maven on Mac <acronym>OSX</acronym>, the main differences being the
      installation location and the setting of an environment variable. This
      book assumes a Maven installation directory of <filename>c:\Program
      Files\apache-maven-${maven.version}</filename>, but it won't make a
      difference if you install Maven in another directory as long as you
      configure the proper environment variables. Once you've unpacked Maven
      to the installation directory, you will need to set two environment
      variables—<envar>PATH</envar> and <envar>M2_HOME</envar>. To set these
      environment variables from the command-line, type in the following
      commands:</para>

      <screen>C:\Users\tobrien &gt; <command>set M2_HOME=c:\Program Files\apache-maven-${maven.version}</command>
C:\Users\tobrien &gt; <command>set PATH=%PATH%;%M2_HOME%\bin</command></screen>

      <para>Setting these environment variables on the command-line will allow
      you to run Maven in your current session, but unless you add them to the
      System environment variables through the control panel, you'll have to
      execute these two lines every time you log into your system. You should
      modify both of these variables through the Control Panel in Microsoft
      Windows.<!--TODO: Document process of setting environment variables in the window control panel system dialog.--></para>
    </section>

    <section id="installation-sect-maven-linux">
      <title>Installing Maven on Linux</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>installing Maven</primary>

          <secondary>on Linux</secondary>
        </indexterm>To install Maven on a Linux machine follow the exact
      procedure outlined in <xref
      linkend="installation-sect-maven-osx" />.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="installation-sect-bsd">
      <title>Installing Maven on FreeBSD or OpenBSD</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>installing Maven</primary>

          <secondary>on FreeBSD</secondary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>installing Maven</primary>

          <secondary>on OpenBSD</secondary>
        </indexterm>To install Maven on a FreeBSD or OpenBSD machine, follow
      the exact procedure outlined in <xref
      linkend="installation-sect-maven-osx" />.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="installation-sect-test-install">
    <title>Testing a Maven Installation</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>installing Maven</primary>

        <secondary>verifying installation</secondary>
      </indexterm>Once Maven is installed, you can check the version by
    running <command>mvn -v</command> from the command-line. If Maven has been
    installed, you should see something resembling the following
    output.</para>

    <screen>$ <command>mvn -v</command>
Apache Maven 2.2.0 (r788681; 2009-06-26 08:04:01-0500)
Java version: 1.5.0_19
Java home: /System/Library/Frameworks/JavaVM.framework/Versions/1.5.0/Home
Default locale: en_US, platform encoding: MacRoman
OS name: "mac os x" version: "10.5.7" arch: "i386" Family: "unix"
</screen>

    <para>If you see this output, you know that Maven is available and ready
    to be used. If you do not see this output, and your operating system
    cannot find the <command>mvn</command> command, make sure that your
    <envar>PATH</envar> environment variable and <envar>M2_HOME</envar>
    environment variable have been properly set.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="installation-sect-upgrade">
    <title>Upgrading a Maven Installation</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>upgrading Maven</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Apache Maven</primary>

        <secondary>upgrading</secondary>
      </indexterm>If you've installed Maven on a Mac OSX or Unix machine
    according to the details in <xref lang=""
    linkend="installation-sect-maven-osx" /> and <xref
    linkend="installation-sect-maven-linux" />, it should be easy to upgrade
    to newer versions of Maven when they become available. Simply install the
    newer version of Maven (<filename>/usr/local/maven-2.future</filename>)
    next to the existing version of Maven
    (<filename>/usr/local/maven-${maven.version}</filename>). Then switch the
    symbolic link <filename>/usr/local/maven</filename> from
    <filename>/usr/local/maven-${maven.version}</filename> to
    <filename>/usr/local/maven-2.future</filename>. Since, you've already set
    your <varname>M2_HOME</varname> variable to point to
    <filename>/usr/local/maven</filename>, you won't need to change any
    environment variables.</para>

    <para>If you have installed Maven on a Windows machine, simply unpack
    Maven to <filename>c:\Program Files\maven-2.future</filename> and update
    your <varname>M2_HOME</varname> variable.</para>

    <note>
      <para>If you have any customizations to the global
      <filename>settings.xml</filename> in <filename>M2_HOME/conf</filename>,
      you will need to copy this <filename>settings.xml</filename> to the
      <filename>conf</filename> directory of the new Maven
      installation.</para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="installation-sect-getting-help">
    <title>Getting Help with Maven</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>online resources</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Apache Maven</primary>

        <secondary>getting help</secondary>
      </indexterm>While this book aims to be a comprehensive reference, there
    are going to be topics we will miss and special situations and tips which
    are not covered. While the core of Maven is very simple, the real work in
    Maven happens in the plugins, and there are too many plugins available to
    cover them all in one book. You are going to encounter problems and
    features which have not been covered in this book; in these cases, we
    suggest searching for answers at the following locations:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><ulink
        url="http://maven.apache.org">http://maven.apache.org</ulink></term>

        <listitem>
          <para><indexterm>
              <primary>Maven web site</primary>
            </indexterm><indexterm>
              <primary>Apache Maven</primary>

              <secondary>project web site</secondary>
            </indexterm>This will be the first place to look, the Maven web
          site contains a wealth of information and documentation. Every
          plugin has a few pages of documentation and there are a series of
          "quick start" documents which will be helpful in addition to the
          content of this book. While the Maven site contains a wealth of
          information, it can also be a frustrating, confusing, and
          overwhelming. There is a custom Google search box on the main Maven
          page that will search known Maven sites for information. This
          provides better results than a generic Google search.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maven User Mailing List</term>

        <listitem>
          <para><indexterm>
              <primary>users mailing list</primary>
            </indexterm><indexterm>
              <primary>Apache Maven</primary>

              <secondary>users mailing list</secondary>
            </indexterm>The Maven User mailing list is the place for users to
          ask questions. Before you ask a question on the user mailing list,
          you will want to search for any previous discussion that might
          relate to your question. It is bad form to ask a question that has
          already been asked without first checking to see if an answer
          already exists in the archives. There are a number of useful mailing
          list archive browsers, we've found Nabble to the be the most useful.
          You can browse the User mailing list archives here: <ulink
          url="http://www.nabble.com/Maven---Users-f178.html">http://www.nabble.com/Maven---Users-f178.html</ulink>.
          You can join the user mailing list by following the instructions
          available here <ulink
          url="http://maven.apache.org/mail-lists.html">http://maven.apache.org/mail-lists.html</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><ulink
        url="http://www.sonatype.com">http://www.sonatype.com</ulink></term>

        <listitem>
          <para><indexterm>
              <primary>Sonatype</primary>
            </indexterm>Sonatype maintains an online copy of this book and
          other tutorials related to Apache Maven.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
</chapter>
